## Thiwanka Alahakoon

Department of Mechanical Engineering Faculty of Engineering University of Peradeniya Sri Lanka

☑ thiwanka.alahakoon@eng.pdn.ac.lk

**\** +94 76 460 3427

in thiwanka-ala

**O** tettolizer

## Research Interests

I am passionate about exploring the intersections of origami structures, 3D modeling, simulations, robotics, AI, and computer vision. My focus lies in research and development that combines these technologies to push the boundaries of innovation, especially in automobile, aerospace, and additive manufacturing engineering. Driven by curiosity, I aim to create integrated solutions that tackle complex challenges in smart, adaptive systems.

## Teaching Experience

#### Teaching Assistant

University of Peradeniya

Jan 2024 - Present

Department of Mechanical Engineering

 Supervise Engineering Drawing (manual and AutoCAD) and Machine Design (SolidWorks) sessions, Mechatronics Systems Labs etc. focusing on practical knowledge and development of critical thinking.

Visiting Lecturer

Middlesex University Oct 2024 - Present

Middlesex University, Australian College of Business and Technology, Kandy.

o teaching sessions on "Calculus and Algebra", "Mechanics" & "Physics"

Casual Instructor

University of Peradeniya

Oct 2023 - Dec 2024

Department of Mechanical Engineering

 Led sessions on Design and Innovation, focusing on 3D modeling and conceptual project design using Solid-Works, and supervised mechatronics labs with PLC, Arduino, and LabView.

## Working Experience

#### **Autonomation Engineer Intern**

MAS Intimates Rathmalana

Jan 2022 - June 2022

o Gained hands-on experience in 3D modeling, Arduino programming, and product development, enhancing skills in DFMA and integrating academic knowledge with real-world engineering challenges.

#### Education

## University of Sri Jayewardenepura

5th Oct 2024 - Present

MSc in Computer Science (Reading)

o Coursework: Data Structures and Algorithms, Computer System Architecture, Computer Graphics and Image Processing, Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning etc.

#### University of Peradeniya

Nov 2018 - Dec 2024

BSc(Hons) in Mechanical Engineering

- ∘ GPA: 3.1/4.0 [Second Class Lower Division] (Transcript 🗹 & Degree Certificate 🗹)
- o Coursework: Digital Design, Engineering Design and Innovation, Differential Equations, Programming Methodology, Control Systems, Embedded Systems, etc.

## Dharmaraja College, Kandy

Jan 2009 - Aug 2017

Secondary Education

- o A/L 2017 (Physical Stream)- Combined Mathematics (A), Physics (A), Chemistry (B) (Results 🗹)
- o O/L 2014 8A's & 1B (Results ∠)
- Junior Prefect Board (2012), Treasurer of Astronomical Society (2015-2016), Media Coordinator of Science Society (2015 - 2016) (Recommendation Letter 2)

## Ongoing Projects

## Sensor Bubble for Vegetable Carrier

March 2024 - Present

An IoT project to develop a sensory system with 3D modeling and sensors to monitor environmental conditions of food during transport, aiming to identify and address packaging solutions.

# Enhancing RAFT [Recurrent All-Pairs Field Transforms] with Attention-Based May 2024 – Present Pyramid Networks for Improved Optical Flow Estimation

• Enhancing RAFT with Attention-Based Pyramid Networks improves optical flow estimation by integrating attention mechanisms and multi-scale processing for more accurate and detailed motion analysis.

#### Research

## Design optimization of Origami-Inspired Airbag for landing and crash protection.

- Conducted a literature review on origami-inspired airbag systems, analyzing various folding patterns like Miura Ori, Hexa-Tri, and Huffman Waterbomb for their crash absorption and deployment efficiency, using Python to create SVGs and simulating them with the Origami Simulator, which provided insights into optimizing compact, efficient airbags and advancing vehicle safety technology.
- o Tools Used: Python, Origami Simulator

#### **CAN Bus Data Visualization Tool**

- Developed a CAN Data Visualization Tool using Arduino boards and sensors to interpret automotive CAN
  bus data, implementing a two-step process for real-time data visualization on a serial monitor and creating
  graphical representations with MATLAB, while enhancing skills in data processing and integration.
- o Tools Used: MATLAB, Arduino

## **Projects**

#### Programming FPGA for MPSOC Design

- Quartus II and Nios II software build tools are used to program the FPGA to create basic systems on chips, modify the CPU, and create multiprocessor systems on chips.
- o Tools Used: Quartus II, Nios II, FPGA

## Game Jumping Jack

- The project's main objectives include handling interrupts in the AtMega328P microcontroller, serial connection, saving data in EEP-ROM, and utilizing sensors
- o Tools Used: AVR

## Design and model of a Carrot Slicer

- Utilized standard techniques and SolidWorks software to design and model the project, incorporating innovative methods inspired by survey findings. This approach allowed for the integration of data-driven insights into the project's development.
- o Tools Used: SolidWorks

## Skills

**Programming:** C, Python, MATLAB, HTML, AVR, R

**Softwares:** Solidworks, Matlab Simulink, Ansys Fluent, Proteus, Adobe Eagle, Autocad, Photoshop, Arduino, MS Project, MS Office

**Soft Skills:** Time Management, Problem-solving, Documentation, Engaging Presentation, Leadership, Critical thinking & Problem Solving etc.

## Certificates

- 2021 Lean Management for engineers' white belt course, Institue of Lean and Green Solutions (PVT) LTD. )
- 2012 International Olympiad Training Programme, The Department of Education of Central Province

#### Achievements

- 2023 Participation, IESL Student Chapter Cad Eager 3d Modeling Competition
- 2022 University Colors, Hockey UOP
- 2017 High Distinction, Sri Lankan Mathematics Olympiad
- 2016 High Distinction, Australian National Chemistry Quiz Senior Division
- 2016 High Distinction, Sri Lankan Mathematics Olympiad
- 2014 High Distinction, Australian National Chemistry Quiz Junior Division
- 2014 High Distinction, Sri Lankan Mathematics Olympiad

## Volunteering

#### Foundation Of Astronomical Studies And Explorations (FASE)

Oct 2017 - Present

- Contributing to the promotion of astronomy through diverse initiatives such as astronomical nights, public lectures, and workshops, and supporting FASE's mission to foster astronomical knowledge among Sri Lankan students and the general public.
- o Roles: Member, Editor, Vice President, Advisory Board Member

#### Rotaract Club, University of Peradeniya

Jun 2019 - Jun 2022

- Chair of the 'Hanthana Hendewa 20' fundraising project and contributor to the 'Reach For Water' Project, aimed at preventing Chronic Kidney Disease in Sri Lanka's dry zone.
- o Roles: Member

## Arunella Social Service Project

Jan 2019 - Nov 2023

- Participated in a project by the Engineering Students Union of the University of Peradeniya aimed at improving underprivileged schools in Sri Lanka, including teaching science and mathematics to O/L students at Vimalarathne Kumaragama Maha Vidyalaya in 2020 and engaging in fundraising efforts in 2023 to support the redevelopment of public restrooms and the restoration of the library roof at Wewathenne Maha Vidyalaya, Gampola.
- o Roles: Teacher, Fundraiser

## Extra Curricular

- 2023 Champions, Sri Lankan University Games (SLUG) Hockey Sri-Lanka
- 2022 University Colors, Hockey UOP
- 2022 2nd Runners-Up, Inter University Games Hockey Sri-Lanka
- 2019 University Half-Colors, Hockey UOP
- 2020 Runners-UP, Rajarata 6's Hockey Championship RUSL
- 2019 2nd Runners-UP, Mora 9's Hockey Championship UOM
- 2019 Champions, Sri Lankan University Games (SLUG) Hockey Sri-Lanka

## References

Prof.Asanga Rathnaweera
Department Head/ Professor
Department of Mechanical Engineering,
University of Peradeniya.
asangar@pdn.ac.lk \(\mathbb{L}\)
(+94) 81 239 3600

Prof. S.D.G.S.P.Gunawardene Senior Lecturer/ Professor Department of Mechanical Engineering, University of Peradeniya. sdgspg@eng.pdn.ac.lk ☎ (+94) 70 321 5033